Finding aid for the Xavier University Master Building Plans collection
Xavier University Archives and Special Collections
Xavier University Master Building Plans collection
1915-2013
Xavier University Archives and Special Collections Phone: 513-745-4821 http://www.xavier.edu/cm/archives
Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio)
2.5 linear feet (6 boxes)
This collection consists of documents, brochures and other materials pertaining to eleven major building projects undertaken at Xavier University since the purchase of the Avondale property in 1911. Most of these projects involved the construction or major renovation of several buildings at the same time, and several were accompanied by a capital gifts campaign to underwrite the work.
XUA-53
History of Master Building Plans at Xavier University
There are documents concerning eleven master building plans found in this collection. Planning from 1915-16 through 2012 is included.
Scope and Content
Eleven master building plans and/or associated documents are included in this collection.
Those building plans and/or associated documents are the following:
1. 1915-1916: "The Greater St. Xavier College: Proposed Plans of the New Buildings in Avondale"
2. 1920's:"The St. Xavier Foundation: Dormitories for St. Xavier College, Avondale"
3. 1949: "Xavier Steps into the Future: Ten Steps into the Future"
4. 1951: "Xavier University Fund and Good Will Campaign"
5. 1956: "Long-Range Development Program for Xavier University"
6. 1964: "Xavier's Ten Year Plan"
7. 1983: "Xavier University Planning Study of 1983" (Dober and Consultants)
8. 1988-91: "Master Plan Report of KZF, Inc."
9. 1996-99: "Hinkle, Schmidt and Alumni Halls Planning Study"
10. 2003-10: "James Hoff Academic Quadrangle: Smith Hall, Conaton Learning Commons, Alter Hall and McDonald Library"
11.1999-2012: East Campus Development
Statement of Arrangement
This collection is arranged by series according to the chronological occurrence of each master building plan. Those series are: Series I: Plans of New Buildings in Avondale, 1915-1916; Series II: Dormitories for St. Xavier College, Avondale, 1920s; Series III: Xavier Steps into the Future, 1949; Series IV: Xavier Fund and Good Will Campaign, 1951; Series V: Long Range Development Program, 1956; Series VI: Xavier's Ten Year Plan, 1964; Series VII: Xavier Planning Study (Dober and Associates), 1983; Series VIII: Master Plan Report by KZF, Inc., 1988-1991; Series IX: Hinkle, Schmidt, and Alumni Hall Planning Study, 1996-1999; Series X: James Hoff Academic Quadrangle, 2003-2010; Series XI: East Campus Development, 1999-2012
Related Material
Materials dealing with the capital gifts campaigns associated with various master building plans can be found in another collection. Please contact the archives staff.
Restrictions on Access
This collection has restricted access. Please contact the Xavier University Archives staff.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Organizations/Corporations:
Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio)-- Planning; Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio)-- Buildings
Detailed Description of The Collection
- Series I: The Greater St. Xavier College: Proposed Plans, 1915-1916
  - Plans of New Buildings in Avondale, 1915-1916 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    This folder contains: 1. The Greater St. Xavier College: Proposed Plans of the New Buildings in Avondale (brochure); 2. Proposed Museum on the Avondale Campus (newspaper article).
- Series II: The St. Xavier Foundation: Dormitories, 1920s
  - Dormitories for St. Xavier College, Avondale, 1927 April 8; undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    This folder contains correspondence and a brochure "The St. Xavier Foundation: Dormitories for St. Xavier College, Avondale."
- Series III: Xavier Steps into the Future, 1949
  - Xavier Steps into the Future, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    This folder contains: 1. "Xavier Steps into the Future: Ten Steps into the Future" (brochure); 2. Newspaper articles and drawings of proposed buildings for the future.
- Series IV: Xavier University Fund and Good Will Campaign, 1951
  - Xavier Fund and Good Will Campaign, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    This folder contains newspaper articles, brochures and pictures.
- Series V: Long-Range Development Program, 1956
  - Long-Range Development Program, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    This folder contains brochures, newspaper articles and pictures about proposed buildings.
- Series VI: Xavier's Ten Year Plan, 1964
  - Xavier's Ten Year Plan, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    This folder contains newspaper articles with photos.
- Series VII: Xavier University Planning Study (Dober and Consultants), 1983
  - The Xavier Planning Study (Dober), 1983 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    This folder contains "The Xavier University Planning Study of 1983," a campus plan prepared by Dober and Associates, Inc., Planning Consultants.
- Series VIII: Master Plan Report of KZF, Inc., 1988-1991
  - Master Plan Report of KZF, Inc., 1988-1991 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    This folder contains pages 1 to 87 of the Master Plan Report.
  - Master Plan Report of KZF, Inc., 1988-1991 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    This folder contains pages 88 to 174 of the Master Plan Report.
  - Master Plan Report of KZF, Inc., 1988-1991 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    This folder contains the appendix "Meeting Minutes" of the Master Plan Report,
  - Master Plan Report by KZF, Inc., 1988-1991 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    This folder contains Project Meeting Minutes, M 18, March 3, 1988 to M 17, March 2, 1988, of the Master Plan Report.
  - Master Plan Report by KZF, Inc., 1988-1991 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    This folder contains additional minutes and other documents from the Master Plan Report.
  - Master Plan Report by KZF, Inc., 1988-1991 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    This folder contains brochures describing the Science Center.
- Series IX: Hinkle, Schmidt and Alumni Halls Planning Study, 1996-1999
  - Hinkle, Schmidt, and Alumni Hall Planning Study, 1996 September 17 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    This folder contains "Hinkle, Schmidt and Alumni Hall Planning Study," prepared by KZF, Inc. This project was in conjunction with the Century Campaign.
- Series X: James Hoff Academic Quadrangle: Smith Hall, Conaton Learning Commons, Alter Hall and McDonald Library, 2003-2010
  - James Hoff Academic Quadrangle: Library Planning Committee, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Xavier University Learning Commons: Collections, Connections, Conversations and Community, 2003 May 20 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Learning Commons: Instructional Technology Services, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Library and Learning Commons, Final Report (Draft), 2003 December (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Facilities Assessment and Recommendations Steering Committee Final Report, 2004 May (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Board of Trustee Committees and Full Board PowerPoint Presentations and Renderings, 2004 May (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Facilities Assessment and Recommendation Steering Committee records, 2005-2006 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    This folder includes a various documents by Shepley Bulfinch Richardson & Abbott relating to the campus master plan.
  - Facilities Assessment and Recommendations Steering Committee Version 1, Part 1, 2003-2004 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Facilities Assessment and Recommendation Steering Committee Version 1, Part 2, 2003-2004 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Facilities Assessment and Recommendation Steering Committee Version 2, Part 1, 2003-2004 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Facilities Assessment and Recommendation Steering Committee Version 2, Part 2, 20003-2004 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Facilities Assessment and Recommendation Steering Committee records, 2006 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Facilities Assessment and Recommendation Steering Committee records, 2006 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Learning Commons Planning, 2007-2009 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Learning Commons Planning, 2007-2009 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Learning Commons Planning, 2007-2009 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Campus Master Plan: Shepley, Bulfinch, Richardson and Abbott, 2005-2006 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Campus Master Plan: Shepley, Bulfinch, Richardson and Abbott (Copy Two), 2005-2006 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Brochures, 2007 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    This folder contains two brochures. One is entitled "Hoff Academic Quad, Phase 1 :Program" by Shepley, Bulfinch, Richardson and Abbott (February, 2007). The other brochure is entitled "Creating a National Model of Excellence: To See Great Wonders, The Campaign for Xavier (undated).
  - Various Documents, 2008 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    This folder contains: 1. Correspondence and other records from 2008 concerning the construction of the Quad. 2. Groundbreaking Celebration materials (September 26, 2008).
  - Hoff Quad Documents, 2008 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    This folder contains: 1. Schematic Design Submission for Hoff Academic Quad, Phase 1 (January 11, 2008) 2. Hoff Academic Quad, "Partnering Session" (April 24, 2008)
  - Various Document Concerning the Quad, 2009-2010 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    This folder contains the following: 1. Correspondence and other records pertaining to the construction of the Quad (2009) 2. Correspondence and other records ;pertaining to the construction of the Quad (2010) 3. Community Celebration of Xavier's Hoff Academic Quadrangle (September 24, 2010)
- Series XI: East Campus Development, 1999-2012
  The East Campus refers to the land bounded by Montgomery Road on the east, Dana Avenue on the south, Cleneay Avenue on the north and the Commons Residence Hall along with the Smith Hall parking lot on the west.. Xavier gradually acquired this land during the late 1990s and early 2000s. Plans to develop it began in 1999 and continued until the University Station opened for business in August, 2014.
  This collection consists of correspondence and other records pertaining to: 1. The acquisition of the BASF property at the corner of Dana and Montgomery in March, 2000. 2. The proposed development plan submitted by the Collegiate Partners Development Team (January 12, 2007) 3. The implosion of the Zumbiel plant on Cleneay Avenue (March 22, 2008) 4. The Xavier Square project and its cancellation in December, 2008. 5. The University Station project, 2012-2014 6. Documents and letters concerning other attempts to develop the property.
  - Correspondence and Documents concerning the East Campus, 1999-2000 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence and Documents concerning the East Campus, 2001-2003 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - East Campus Development Proposal Addendum, 2007 January 12 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    This document was composed by the Miller Valentine Group and Towne Properties (Collegiate Partners Development Team).
  - East Campus Development Documents, 2008 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    This folder contains the following items: 1. Correspondence and documents concerning the East Campus (2008) 2. Implosion of the Zumbiel Plant and the Demolition of the Norwood Cafe and the houses on Ledgewood (CD-R) 3. Cancellation of the Xavier Square Project (December 2008)
  - University Station Project, 2012 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    This folder includes the document "Mixed Use Development at Dana & Montgomery: Project Vision" published by Messer FRCH/Design Worldwide.